Hello בוקר טוב. boker tov. Alright, so today's דף daf is כ"ח.
kaf chet. We pick up with the משנה mishnah at the bottom
of כ"ז kaf zayin עמוד ב', amud bet,
and we are still dealing with actually that משנה mishnah at the
end of yesterday, but let's read it again quickly today. We're dealing
again with this question about when army—a troop comes into a city,
are you afraid that the women were raped? And although the משנה
mishnah makes it sound like basically all the women we are afraid
if they're married to כהנים, kohanim, the גמרא Gemara effectively makes it
moot. I mean, the משנה mishnah already has that you believe a
single witness except maybe her maidservant was debated, her husband you wouldn't,
but the גמרא Gemara then makes the circumstances so narrow that it
almost would never apply. But keeping within the line of the משנה,
mishnah,
which did see it as a broader application and not believing her
or her husband, we had the following משנה mishnah we might as
well just read it again, bottom of כ"ז kaf zayin עמוד ב'.
amud bet. אמר זכריה בן הקצב: Amar Zechariah ben HaKatzav: המעון הזה,
Hamaon hazeh,
by this Zechariah, excuse me, by this by this temple. So questions
probably post-חורבן, churban, but I forgot to check out when he would
live. Anyway, there's a case where non-Jews presumably the Romans entered into
to the city.
And he said, לא זזה ידה מתוך ידי משעה שנכנסו עובדי כוכבים
לירושלים ועד שיצאו. lo zaza yada mitoch yadi mishe'sha nichnesu ovdei kochavim
li'Yerushalayim v'ad she'yatzu.
From the time the non-Jews entered into Jerusalem—I don't know if this
is חורבן הבית Churban HaBayit or later, maybe time of בר כוכבא—her
Bar Kochba hand never left my hand so she was not raped,
I was with her the whole time. אמרו לו, Amru lo, the
Rabbis said to him, אין אדם מעיד על עצמו. ein adam me'id
al atzmo. You can't testify for yourself; here it's about your wife
but it's about helping yourself and her status vis-a-vis yourself, and therefore
you are not believed.
Interestingly, even though basically he and she both know she isn't raped,
it's sort of like we're not going to let them continue to
live together, right? So that's fascinating. That gets to the question about
to what degree do the Rabbis get involved in marriage situations, and
it's one thing to say if somebody is known—is clearly violating and
we're going to go ahead like a כהן kohen is married to
a גרושה, gerusha, it's another thing if they both say, we know
what we're doing is totally okay, we know the facts. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Was it his daughter or was it his wife?
No, I think—what would it have helped if that was a daughter?
Let's say
me and a daughter. At least keep it in the family honor
but it's not really—yeah, well so a daughter is fine we said.
תנא: Tanna: ואף על פי כן ייחד לה בית בחצירו. v'af al
pi chen yiched lah bayit bechatzeiro. Even though they—even though they were
forbidden, they were forbidden to continue living together, she stayed within the
sort of family compound, he had a house in the yard, she
had a house in the yard. וכשהיא יוצאה יוצאה בראש בניה וכשהיא
נכנסת נכנסת בסוף בניה. uch'she'hi yotza yotza berosh b'nei uch'she'hi nichneset nichneset
besof b'nei. So presumably they didn't get divorced, they just stopped living
together, and or I don't know, maybe they got divorced. Anyway, when
she would leave she would leave at the head of the kids,
and when she would come back she would come back at the
front of the—at the front of the family—at the front of the
group, because—so she should never be left alone in the courtyard together
with him. בעי אביי. ba'ei Abaye. So אביי Abaye asked, מהו לעשות
בגרושה כן? mahu la'asot begerusha kein?
How about dealing—doing the same thing by a גרושה? gerusha? A כהן
kohen divorced his wife and can she continue to live in the
courtyard in a way that prevent there from being ייחוד? yichud? So
it would be interesting why you would divorce and then they'd want
to continue living together, but you know, maybe who knows what the
reasons are, maybe he needs her to continue to raise the kids
or something of that nature.
התם הוא דבשבויה הקילו, hatam hu debishvuyah hikilu, there was a case
that a woman was taken captive or whatever, I mean it's in
the category of שבויה shvuyah although she wasn't taken captive, it was
the non-Jews entered, you know, the—the enemy entered into the city. But
there they're lenient because they don't know for sure that she was
raped. אבל הכא לא, aval hacha lo, but here no, we know
she's definitely forbidden to him. או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo
shna, maybe it won't make a difference. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear. דתניא, ditanya, we taught in the ברייתא: Baraita: המגרש אשתו
לא תנשא בשכנותה. Hamgaresh ishto lo tinnasei bishchunutah. If a man divorces
his wife she should not get married and live, you know, for
the purpose of settling within the same neighborhood.
Question—yeah, question of exactly what constitutes a שכונה. shchunah. רש"י Rashi says
because they all know each other's body languages and hints and whatever
and therefore maybe, you know, some of that old attraction is still
there and they'll find a way to—to sleep together and to have
an affair and therefore—and she's now married to another man. So therefore
we're afraid that it's a little bit too much asking for trouble
having them together in this—you know, having this previously married couple who
are now married to other people live close to one another. Anyway—because
it's
too easy. Ah yeah, question how you define שכונה. shchunah. תוספות Tosafot
says שכונה shchunah means within three houses. ואם היה כהן לא תדור
עמו במבוי.
v'im haya kohen lo
tadur immo bemavui. And if he's a כהן, kohen, she cannot live
with him in the same מבוי. mavui. He even when—even if she's
not remarried. He divorced his wife, she can't be within the same
מבוי. mavui. מבוי mavui is like a courtyard—is like—you have all the
houses open up into a yard and all the yards open up
into a מבוי. mavui. מבוי mavui excuse me is more like an
alley. So that's a—you know, so that's a street that has multiple
courtyards opening up into it. תוספות Tosafot says that's even
more—you know, that's even a larger area than— because since she's not
married to another man, you're more afraid that, you know, that they'll
get back together and now she's a גרושה. grusha. So this כהן
kohen divorced his wife, she can't even be in the same, in
the same alley, you know, in the same, I don't know what
to call it, not a courtyard but whatever section of the neighborhood,
okay, section of the town. Because so, דוקא, davka, because even when
she's not married, but it's also a bigger because she's a גרושה,
grusha, but it's a bigger concern that she's not married, that they,
that something might happen. So that basically answers that question, that the
normal case of a כהן kohen and a גרושה, grusha, they cannot,
not only can she not live in the courtyard, you know, where
multiple houses open up, you know, and basically the, right, the case
to the משנה, mishnah, the case of the ברייתא braita was בית
בחצרו, bayit bechatzeiro, again, like you know, the way it was structured,
we did this when we did עירובין, Eruvin, is that you have
a yard and you had sort of houses surrounding the yard. So
when it was said, when it says that this case of the
husband כהן kohen whose wife people think was raped but he and
she says that she wasn't, so that's another house that opens up
into the same court, you know, like yard, like you know, you
should think like like a court, you know, like of a street
courtyard but what we call a court, like you know, the street
goes into a circular place and a lot of houses open up
into it, right, so that's בחצר. bechatzer. This is the מבוי, mavoi,
the מבוי mavoi is even a larger area, that's where all of
those courtyards open up into. Alright, so if it's a real case
of a גרושה grusha and not just a case of a שבויה,
shvuya, they can't even be in the same מבוי. mavoi. אם היה
כפר קטן, Im haya kfar katan,
if it was a כהן, kohen, which was the case that we
were asking. אם היה כפר קטן, Im haya kfar katan, if it
was a little village, דהא מעשה ואמרו כפר קטן נידון כשכונה, Deha
maaseh veamru kfar katan nidon keshchunah, that's like a שכונה, shchunah, of
course the ב"ח Bach switches it כמבוי. kemavoi. But anyway, a little
village might be the same as, you know, as one of these
sections in a larger town. Okay now, מי נדחה מפני מי? Mi
nidche mipnei mi? Now basically if we're saying they can't live in
the same neighborhood, you know, in the same sort of small section,
or they can't live in the same whether it's a שכונה shchunah
or a מבוי, mavoi, who has to move? Okay, so תא שמע,
ta shma, come
and hear, now it sounds like she's the one that can't move,
it said in her לא תדור לא תינשא.
lo tador
lo tinnase.
So but let's take a look, תא שמע, ta shma, come and
hear,
דתניא, detanya, היא נדחית מפניו, hi nidcheit mipanav, she has to, she's
pushed away from his presence, ואינו נדחה מפניה, veino nidche mipaneha, he
doesn't have to move because of her. Okay, which is like interesting,
why should we assume that, basically because we assume that, you know,
if she got divorced, she's the one leaving the house, ויצאה מביתו,
veyatza mibeito, right, that was the part of the reality, he's staying
in the house, so therefore it's a question where's she going to
resettle. ואם היתה חצר שלה, Veim hayta chatzer shelah, let's say she
owned the house, she owned the yard, הוא נדחה מפניה, hu nidche
mipaneha, then he's the one that has to move. Okay, איבעיא להו,
Iba'ya lehu, so they asked a question, היתה חצר של שניהם מהו?
hayta chatzer shel shneihem mahu? Let's say it was jointly owned property,
right? So she says, "I want to move to this house in
the חצר," chatzer, and he says, "No, I want," you know, so
basically it's like they both want to live in the חצר chatzer
in different houses, and they both have a right to the חצר
chatzer because they're both partial owners, so who has to move? So
תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear, היא נדחית מפניו, hi nidcheit
mipanav, she's pushed away from him. במאי עסקינן, Bimai askinan, what are
we talking about? אילימא בחצר שלו, Ilima bechatzer shelo, if it's his
courtyard, פשיטא, pishita, of course, you know, it's his courtyard, he says,
"צאי, tzei, lady, you're the one who has to move." ואלא בחצר
שלה, Ve'ela bechatzer shelah, let's say it's her courtyard, והתניא אם היתה
חצר שלה הוא נדחה מפניה, vehatanya im hayta chatzer shelah hu nidche
mipaneha, if it's her courtyard he's the one that has to move.
אלא לאו, Ela lav, what's the case? כי האי גוונא, Ki hai
gavna, must be it's both of their courtyards, and nevertheless even though
they both jointly own it, we somehow give say that he gets
to stay and you're the one that has to move.
So we ask a question, "Wait a minute, so like in other
words there was separate title to the house and to the courtyard?"
"Apparently, yes. Apparently you could own a whole courtyard." "Okay, and then
it's a question about, so she says I, you know, want to
be in this house in the courtyard and he says no."
"I, you could own a house and your neighbor could own the
courtyard."
"I guess, I don't know, possible." דילמא, Dilma, so the גמרא Gemara
says, "מאי לאו כי האי גוונא?" mai lav ki hai gavna? The
גמרא Gemara says, "No. דילמא דאוגר מיגר." dilma de'oger miger. No, maybe
it's a rental, meaning maybe if she actually is a partial ownership,
then she can say, "I have an entitlement to stay here," and
I don't know who's going to have to move before whom, but
you know, but anyway that's one thing. If they're both just rented,
then nobody has a real sort of, you know, real rights to
the place, then we'll say that she'll she's the one that has
to move. So מאי הוי עלה, mai hava alah, what was the
conclusion? If they really have joint ownership, then who do we who
has to move? תא שמע, Ta shma, so come
and hear, הנה ה' מטלטלך טלטלה גבר, Hinei Hashem metaltelcha taltela gever,
God is going to cause you to exile yourself around, so I
told you we're dealing with exile in this week's in this דף
daf to, you know, to move around like the moving around of
a man.
ואמר רב טלטולי דגברא קשי מדאיתתא, Ve'amar Rav taltulei de'gavra kashi mide'itata,
since this was a curse, it shows you that for a man
to be dispossessed is harder for than for a woman to be
dispossessed. So therefore we're going to favor the man and say that
she's the one that has to move, which does not seem too
fair, but you know, especially because if you think about it that
the woman is the one raising the kids and so on, you
know, if that were the case then it would tend to be
easier for the man to move. On the other hand, the whole
nature of a
patriarchy... therefore
in such a case, you know, of course this also imagines a
scenario where they both could have their own house in the same
courtyard and nevertheless it's assumed to be that we have to ask
one of them to move and we're going to ask her to
be the one to move. Yeah.
The other side of that is the woman is called the בית.
bayit. Right, that's also true, yeah. I mean, that is that irony.
You're right. I mean, the woman is the one that's called the
בית, bayit, the woman's the one that raises the kids, but like
the societal construct is that it's the man's house, you know, household.
So it's true, it's ironic. You know.
And in many cases the guy is moving anyway.
I mean in most cases of divorce, it tends to be the
man that winds up moving out. Yeah, today.
Precisely for this reason because the woman needs to be the stability
to raise
the kids and
stay in the state that they've been growing up with.
Exactly. Exactly. Right. All right. All right, moving on. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. So we're still going to deal with these questions. So now
we're sort of in this middle of this digression here about this
concern of, you know, about ex-husband and wives being getting having too
many things to do with one another is it going to lead
to to them, you know, going off and having sex. And it's
particularly a problem if it's either a כהן Kohen and a גרושה
Grushah or a woman who is remarried. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. לוה
הימנה בנכסי אביה Lava heimena binichsei aviha
if when they were married he took out a loan from her
from her father's property meaning רש״י Rashi says it's the property she
brought into the marriage the נכסי מלוג. Nichsei Milog. Okay, but that's
sort of parenthetical. But it basically means he borrowed money from her.
And now they're divorced. And presumably we're dealing with the wife of
a כהן. Kohen.
All those of course things are missing. Anyway, אלא אינה נפרעת אלא
על ידי אחר. Ela einah nifraat ela al yedei acher. She
he only pays up the loan through somebody else, okay, meaning that
they can't basically get together for collecting the loan and paying off
the loan because then they'll get into private and who knows one
thing will lead to another.
But he can go with two other people.
Yeah, exactly. Or he can send people, he can go with other
people, right. Okay, so okay, fine.
And it also means אינה נפרעת einah nifraat that she's not the
one that's pressed, that she sends somebody else there to represent her.
Anyway, אמר רב ששת. Amar Rav Sheshet. Now this this gets even
stranger. די אתו לקמן לדינא De'atu lekaman ledina if they come for
us for a case, a court case, either fighting over some loan
or some other matter, לא מזדקקינן להו. lo mizdakkinnan lehu. We refuse
to to to no, yeah, to sit in to
respond to them. We refuse to basically to hear the case, which
is crazy because, oh, you know, anytime any people have law cases,
I mean nowadays it's always like my lawyer, you know, said I
can't talk to you. But presumably if they're having a law case
they're spending a lot of time arguing and fighting and discussing the
matters and there's going to be a lot of, you know, it's
private time together. So therefore, of course does it make it better
if you refuse to hear the case then all the more so
they'll get together and try to talk the issue out. Like I
don't even understand like, you know, and you you refuse to actually
like what's their choice is like where what's your isn't don't you
have responsibility like to to do דין? Din? You know, I really
don't understand this. רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר amar the concern
is that that
a כהן Kohen and a גרושה Grushah they're going to be spending
time together and his divorced wife and they have a past sexual
relationship so one thing will lead to another they'll have sex. Okay.
But seeing each other in court to if they give the case
and and they see each other.
If they go every single day they're getting together at the courthouse
for their case. So one day they say, hey, you want to
have lunch together, and then whatever, and then oh, there's a hotel
around the corner, whatever, and one thing leads to another. Okay, fine,
I understand the concern, but I understand the concern, I just don't
understand what the alternative is. I mean, give me an advice, say
that you have to do it through some representative, say something. So
רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר שמותי משמתינן להו. amar shamutei mishamttinan lehu.
We put them into like שמתא, shamta, into a minor חרם. cherem.
I don't understand, what's this supposed to do? Like they're not supposed
so so how they I
again, it doesn't make any sense. רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav
Huna breih deRav Yehoshua אמר נגודי נמי מנגדינן להו. amar nagudei nami
menagdinan lehu. We even give them lashes. I don't understand this at
all. Maybe, yeah, exactly. No, I don't know, your
ArtScroll
maybe brings down some interesting things, I haven't had a chance to
look it up, but I find this very strange. אמר רב נחמן
Amar Rav Nachman said רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, תנא דבי אבא רבתי,
Tana d'vei Abba Rabbati, we learned in אבל רבתי Avel Rabbati which
is מסכת שמחות, Masechet Semachot, which is like a collection of Tannaitic
and Amoraic statements around אבילות, aveilut, but but it's we'll take a
look here, it's not really about אבילות. aveilut. במדאמ"ר Bamei devarim amurim
when is this that we can't don't let a כהן Kohen and
his divorced wife spend any time together or hear her court cases
or whatever? שנתגרשה מן הנישואין Shenitgarsha min hanissuinn
if they had been had נישואין nissuinn prior, so they had a
prior sexual relationship. They had actually been living together as husband and
wife. אבל נתגרשה מן האירוסין Aval nitgarsha min haeirussin if they had
only had אירוסין eirussin prior and they had not yet started their
sexual life together, so נפרעת על ידי עצמה nifraat al yedei atzmah
then she can for herself be present when she's coming to collect
the loan. שאין לבו גס בה She'ein libo gas bah because then
he does not feel so like comfortable with her that he is
going that it will lead to them, you know, going off and
having sex. Now ההוא ארוס וארוסתו דאתו לקמיה דרבא Hahu arus va'arusato
de'atu lekamei deRava
let me just finish this, a man and woman who had been
had קידושין kiddushin and again the key factor is that presumably now
they're divorced and presumably now he's a כהן kohen came to רבא
Rava for some type of a court case maybe for collecting a
debt. יתבי רב אדא בר מתנה קמיה Yatvi Rav Adda bar Matna
kamei so רב אדא בר מתנה Rav Adda bar Matna was in
front of him. אוקי רבא שלוחא בינייהו Oki Rava shlucha beinaihu so
רבא Rava here finally we have a solution to this. So what
רבא Rava did was he put a third party in the between
them. So rather than having them talk to one another they would
talk through their either each one had a שליח shaliach that they
would talk through their representative but it sounds like more that there
was a third party so they didn't directly talk to one another.
Well you should tell my husband that blah blah blah. Well my
if my wife would somebody would tell my wife that da da
da so you know people have ways of doing that of talking
to one another without addressing one another.
Mediator what's that phrase?
Yeah but I don't think it's a mediator.
He's not there he's not there to mediate. He is there so
that they can both present their cases in front of the בית
דין beis din without them having to talk to one another. אמר
ליה רב אדא בר מתנה Amar lei Rav Adda bar Matna so
we finally at least see a solution. So רב אדא בר מתנה
Rav Adda bar Matna says ואמר רב נחמן תנא בי רב באסי
v'amar Rav Nachman tana bei Rav Bassi etc. We just thought that
you're not that actually you're not allowed you don't no that when
they are an ארוס arus it's not נישואין nisuin you don't need
it right? אמר ליה כחזינא דקגייסי בהדדי Amar lei k'chazina d'kagaissi b'hadadi
no I see from their body language they're very comfortable with one
another so I'm being a little bit careful here. Okay great. But
so that doesn't tell you will that work even in the case
when they really were נישואין. nisuin. So let's take a look. אמר
ליה Amar lei so the גמרא Gemara says איכא דאמרי ika d'amri
some say לא אוקי רבא שליחא בינייהו. lo oki Rava shlucha beinaihu.
רבא Rava did not require any intermediary. אמר ליה רב אדא בר
מתנה נעקום מר שלוחא בינייהו Amar lei Rav Adda bar Matna neikum
mar shlucha beinaihu why not give them an intermediary? אמר ליה ואמר
רב נחמן תנא בי רב באסי Amar lei v'amar Rav Nachman tana
bei Rav Bassi etc. why do I need an intermediary? They've never
had נישואין. nisuin. אמר ליה הני מילי היכא דלא גייסי בהדדי Amar
lei hani mili heicha d'lo gaissi b'hadadi that's only when they're not
comfortable with one another. אבל הני כחזינא דקא גייסי בהדדי Aval hani
k'chazina d'ka gaissi b'hadadi etc. it's clear that they're very comfortable with
one another so therefore we need to do some types of chaperoning
and some types of intermediaries. Hopefully that would work even in the
case of them having been נישואין nisuin or else it's really crazy.
What's somebody supposed to do forfeit all of their claims because they
can't go to the court case? Yes Michael?
Unless that's trying to say you want to know what the ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael concluded because
in the
other case about not listening to them or giving them whatever
that's
only if there's no intermediary. Okay great so that's what they did.
They used the later case of the גמרא Gemara as a way
of dealing with the difficulty. היו רגילים שמחה.
Havu ragilin simcha. Okay. תניא אידך. Tanya idach.
Yeah I mean you know there's always these questions about this. That
there's a Tannaitic layer and then it was edited Amoraic and then
in the time of the גאונים Geonim like a lot of these
מסכתות קטנות masechtos katanos and so on and the מדרש רבה Midrash
Rabbah all that stuff. Okay. משנה. Mishna. ואלו נאמנים להעיד בגודלן מה
שראו בקוטנן. V'eilu ne'emanim l'ha'id b'godlan mah she'ra'u b'kotnan. Last משנה mishna
of the פרק. perek. ואלו נאמנים להעיד בגודלן מה שראו בקוטנן. V'eilu
ne'emanim l'ha'id b'godlan mah she'ra'u b'kotnan.
So therefore the following are believed to testify when they're adults what
they saw when they were kids. Why is this relevant? I mean
ultimately a lot of this is about personal status and this is
going to tie into the first משנה mishna of the פרק perek
about whether a woman got married when she was a בתולה besulah
or not whether she's entitled to her כתובה kesuvah of 200. You
might remember that was the transition. The whole first פרק perek was
about the husband saying she wasn't a בתולה. besulah. Finds up the
next morning goes to בית דין. beis din. Then the משנה mishna
in the second פרק perek began with the question about that it's
not a question about whether she was a בתולה besulah the first
night it's now 20 years later and they're arguing whether it was
you know whether at that 20 years ago it was a first
marriage or a second now. And then there was a questions about
was there witnesses that she'd you know she had the white dress
and she had the whole wedding party and the whole thing to
indicate that it had been a first marriage or not. Okay so
and then we got into all these discussions about testimony about personal
status and recently women about being raped a lot about women's personal
status but we also did other issues תשעה באב Tisha B'Av now
we tie back to the first משנה mishna going back to this
question. One of the examples here will be this issue or applications
will be this issue of whether that marriage 20 years ago was
a first wedding or not was the first marriage or not. Let's
take a look. ואלו נאמנים להעיד בגודלן מה שראו בקוטנן. V'eilu ne'emanim
l'ha'id b'godlan mah she'ra'u b'kotnan. The following are believed to testify when
they're adults what they saw when they were kids. נאמן אדם לומר
זה כתב ידו של אבא וזה כתב ידו של רבי וזה כתב
ידו של אחי. Ne'eman adam lomar zeh ktav yado shel abba v'zeh
ktav yado shel rebbi v'zeh ktav yado shel achi. Okay somebody can
say I recognize this signature when I was a kid I remember
seeing that that's what my father's signature looked like or that's what
my רבי rebbi's signature looked like or my brother's signature and all
this is for
קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros right in order to to validate the signatures
on a document. וזה כתב ידו של אחי. v'zeh ktav yado shel
achi. זכור הייתי בפלוני Zachor hayiti b'ploni
so that's one category קיום שטרות kiyum shtaros recognizing a signature. Now
you're an adult. Okay by the way I should say the חדוש
chidush of this משנה mishna is the
גמרא Gemara is going to explain that most of these cases are
דרבנן d'rabbanan or for other reasons we don't really need formal testimony.
The assumption of this משנה mishna is is that if we had
a need for normal formal testimony you could not testify even if
now you're an adult for something you saw before you were an
adult. That the same way the giving of testimony what defines somebody
as a כשר kosher witness you know being an adult and so
on is required those criteria are
required for the delivery of testimony the act of testifying. fine, it’s
also it’s also required for actually seeing what you’re testifying about. You
have to be defined as an עד, ed, as a witness at
that time. So if what you witnessed, you witnessed when you were
not a כשר עד, kosher ed, you cannot testify to it now
that you are a כשר עד, kosher ed, right? And then it
raises interesting questions. Let’s say for example I was related to somebody
when I saw something and now I’m not related to him because
it was a relationship based on marriage and now there’s a divorce.
Can I no longer testify, right? So I was a גזלן gazlan
at the time I saw something now I’m not a גזלן. gazlan.
But the משנה mishna assumes that you have to be a כשר
עד kosher ed not just when you testify but when you witness
it. And therefore it’s saying here are the exceptions to the rules.
One exception to the rule is testifying to a signature. If you
witnessed if you saw the signature when you were a kid, you
can testify to it as an adult.
דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot?
Well the גמרא gemara is going to tell you the reason. Now
let’s just go through the משנה mishna here.
דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchuta trumps all?
Yeah we’re not dealing with דינא דמלכותא. dina d'malchuta. I’m sorry. Okay,
that’s number one. Okay, זכור הייתי בפלונית zachur hayiti beplonit and now
we get the tie in back to the earlier משנה. mishna. By
the way it’s very nice that there’s a whole I think like
nice wrapping up because if you remember we shifted from talking about
whether about whether the woman was her first wedding or not a
first wedding to and then we had a case pretty soon after
of witnesses saying oh yes this is our signature but we were
forced, we were minors. So now you have having been a minor
testifying to a signature, right, echoes that case of saying we signed
it and we were minors. And now the next case gets back
to the first משנה mishna of the פרק perek about whether this
was a first wedding for a woman or not. זכור הייתי בפלונית
zachur hayiti beplonit I remember oh yes שרה Sarah 20 years ago
when she got married I was a little kid I remember שיצאה
בהינומא sheyatza behinuma she went out in that whole wedding carriage whatever
the הינומא hinuma was, the whole big production וראשה פרוע verosha parua
and her head was uncovered at the time.
Okay, ושאנו מצפים veshano metzapim no that’s
that’s number two. Okay so I remember that. Okay so testifying that
about a woman whether it was a first wedding or not. That’s
another thing you’re believed about even though you saw it as a
kid. Number three, ושהיה איש פלוני יוצא מבית הספר לטבול לאכול בתרומה
veshayah ish ploni yotze mibeit hasefer litvol leechol bitrumah
I saw a certain person that would leave the the חדר cheder
our school and he would go and go to the מקווה mikvah
and then he would eat תרומה trumah ושהיה חולק עמנו על הגורן
veshayah cholek imanu al hagoren or we were coming
I would go with my dad and we were כהנים kohanim and
this little kid would come along with and also get the food
at the granary and therefore that can be you can learn that
he’s a כהן. kohen. So again notice that that’s echoing cases we
had before about establishing somebody as a כהן. kohen. Okay so a
lot of these cases echo what we had before. Okay so some
type of story that you tell over that you saw it as
a kid that indicates that this other person is a כהן. kohen.
Now והמקום הזה בית הפרס. vehamakom hazeh beit hapras. This is something
we haven’t seen before. This following area is a בית הפרס beit
hapras a place where a grave was plowed over and therefore a
כהן kohen cannot go into it. Now what why is that relevant?
I mean why is that relevant but that’s not similar to the
earlier examples because the earlier examples right you’re not you’re coming to
either be lenient or you mean if all you do is you
say this place is a בית הפרס beit hapras you’re being strict.
To say you believe this kid to say okay no no כהנים
kohanim should work should walk here is not a big חידוש chiddush
that we believe somebody to be strict. So תוספות tosafot explains that
no no you’re being lenient. What happened was we have this huge
this huge plot 20 acres and we know somewhere here there was
a בית הפרס. beit hapras. And since we can’t identify where there’s
a בית הפרס beit hapras we say כהנים kohanim can’t walk in
any of the 20 acres. And then this kid says no no
the בית הפרס beit hapras was right over here. So because he’s
telling you where it was you now allow the כהנים kohanim to
walk in all the rest of the space. Okay so that’s what
you’re going to believe that he saw as a kid ועד כאן
היינו באים בשבת vead kan hayinu baim beshabbat
and we would only go up to this point in שבת shabbat
or we would go even up to this point in שבת shabbat
so you believe him in terms of where the תחומים tchumim are
for the city.
Meaning but that can’t be independently verified? תחום tchum is 2000 אמה?
amah?
Yeah it’s a good question. I was wondering about that too. But
I mean it’s an enormous amount of effort to go ahead and
to and to verify exactly and search out where exactly is the
last house and so on. So you don’t have the time to
do it. It’s ערב שבת erev shabbat and this kid tells you
whatever whatever I remember.
אבל אין אדם נאמן לומר
aval
ein
adam neeman lomar דרך היה לפלוני derech hayah leploni so all that
you’re believed but you’re not believed to say דרך היה לפלוני במקום
הזה. derech hayah leploni bemakom hazeh. Yeah although this field is שמעון’s,
Shimon ראובן Reuven had a path that he was entitled to to
walk through שמעון’s Shimon field. That you’re not believed because that’s a
strict דיני ממונות dinei mamonot issue and you would wind up taking
a path away from שמעון Shimon that’s presumed to be שמעון’s Shimon
and giving it to ראובן. Reuven. Okay or מעמד ומספד היה לפלוני
במקום הזה. maamad umisped hayah leploni bemakom hazeh.
This person although this field is שמעון’s, Shimon ראובן Reuven would have
had a right to or owned this section of the field where
when his they would be taking out the dead to bury for
ראובן’s Reuven
family they would do the whole type of a funeral procession here
and they would have the mourners sit and stand and they’d give
them the ניחומים. nichumim. So he actually had certain either ownership or
certain rights in שמעון’s Shimon field. That you don’t believe because that’s
strict דיני ממונות dinei mamonot and you need strict
עדות. edut. Anything that he’s right when he said I
saw them do
it once? Well yeah I
know he has rights because
of what I witnessed. I witnessed that
ראובן... Reuven... This field belongs to שמעון Shimon and you're trying to
entitle ראובן Reuven to some type of a rights in the field,
that's דיני ממונות. dinei mammonus. You need formal testimony. If the kid
saw it as a kid, he's not a kosher עד. eid. Okay,
so that is nice to emphasize the contrast that the beginning of
the משנה mishnah is a חידוש. chiddush. Okay, yes.
It's interesting that these are cases where he is accepted, they're much
more important situations than money issues.
Yeah, I mean איסור... issur... Marriage, כהן... kohen...
It's true. Well, the marriage issue is still a money issue because
it's how big is her כתובה. kesubah. Okay, but yeah, you're right.
I mean, so let's take a look, so the גמרא's Gemara now
going to explain it.
ושהיה עמו על הגורן, Veshayei immo al hagoren, it can't be a
slave, right, because...
Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to discuss all that. Let's read the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, והוא שיש גדול עמו. vehu sheyesh gadol immo. So all
of these he's not believed as an עד אחד, ed echad, he's
believed together with another witness. So there's a major discussion in the
ראשונים Rishonim which case this is going on. Okay. Certainly it's going
on the first case about verifying signatures. You always need two witnesses
to verify signatures. There's some question that it might be going on
the second case about the guy is a כהן... kohen...
because... do you need him to... you know because if you're saying
he's a כהן kohen does that also lead to נישואין nissuin cases,
you know, מעלה ליוחסין ma'aleh l'yuchsin and יוחסין yuchsin therefore needs two
witnesses? It's not clear how many of the cases this statement is
going on. Minimally it is going on the first case of verifying
the signatures. You need to be somebody else. וצריכא. U'tzricha. Now you
need to say all... and it seems like that because the גמרא
Gemara now focuses specifically on the signature issue. You need all three
examples of the signature: father, brother, and Rebbe. דאשמעינן אביו, D'ashmi'inan aviv,
if you believed about the father's signature משום דשכיח גביה, mishum d'shchiach
gabei, because you know you spent a lot of time with his
father so presumably he had a lot of chance to see the
signature, he really remembers it. אבל רבו לא, Aval rabbo lo, but
not by the Rebbe. דאשמעינן רבו, D'ashmi'inan rabbo, but the Rebbe משום
דאיתא אימתיה דרבו mishum d'isa emteh d'rabbo because he has the fear
of his Rebbe. Not exactly sure what the fear of the Rebbe
does in terms of... but basically means you would never testify about
your Rebbe's signature unless you were like totally certain. Okay. אבל אביו
לא, Aval aviv lo, but not the father. דאשמעינן הני תרתי, D'ashmi'inan
hani tartei, if it just said those two, אביו דשכיח גביה ורבו
דאיתא אימתיה, aviv d'shchiach gabei ve'rabbo d'isa emteh, אבל אחיו, aval achiv,
the brother, that's... the father you always see it and the Rebbe
you're afraid and you would never do it if you weren't sure.
But a brother דלית ליה לא האי ולא האי, d'lais lei lo
hai velo hai, you don't spend necessarily a lot of time, you
assume you're spending more time with your father than with your brother.
Okay, anyway, but you don't necessarily have one or the other. אימא
לא, Eima lo, maybe we wouldn't believe you about the signature, you
know, we wouldn't say you're so certain. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan
that we do. כיון דקיום שטרות מדרבנן, Keivan d'kium shtaros m'drabbanan, now
we explain, since the whole need to validate a שטר shtar is
only rabbinic, הימנו רבנן בדרבנן, heimnu rabbanan b'drabbanan, we were prepared to
believe, you know, the rabbis were prepared to believe this person for
a rabbinic matter. So the first חידוש chiddush is why do we
believe you for קיום שטרות? kium shtaros? Because that is rabbinic and
therefore since at least you're an adult when you're giving the testimony,
it's okay that you saw it as a kid. Now the next
case: זכור אני שהייתי בפלוני שיצאה בהינומא וראשה פרוע, Zachur ani she'hayisi
b'ploni sheyatz'ah b'hinuma veroshah parua, that the... he testifies to oh yeah
it was a first wedding, there was a white wedding dress and
all these types of things, whatever it was, 300 guests, etc.
Her head was exposed, which is important, we'll get back to that
when we deal with the whole issue about woman's head covering. So
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why do we believe? I mean this is
a money issue, 200 or 100, why should we require real witnesses?
כיון דרוב נשים בתולות נישאות, Keivan d'rov nashim besulos nisas,
no, most women get married as virgins, first... most weddings are first
weddings. Therefore, גילוי מילתא בעלמא הוא, gilluy milsa b'alma hu, it's just
the revealing of something, not testimony. Now normally גילוי מילתא בעלמא gilluy
milsa b'alma means that the matter will somehow be revealed on its
own. Okay and we don't necessarily need the testimony. That's not necessarily
true here. It's 20 years later. The matter isn't going to be
revealed on its own. But רש"י Rashi basically says it means that
we don't really need testimony, the testimony is just backing up something
we're pretty much assuming anyway, right? If you look at רש"י, Rashi,
גילוי מילתא בעלמא, כלומר אין הדבר צריך עדות אלא לפרסם שיצא הדין
לאור בלא גמגום. gilluy milsa b'alma, klomar ein hadavar tzarich eidus ela
l'farseim sheyeitzei hadin l'or belo gimgum.
We're really only demanding testimony so that everybody knows that, like, it
validates what we already know. And therefore it's not really an עדות
eidus testimony, so we'll be more lenient.
But if he said they didn't put like that bottle of... that
barrel of
wine?
That's a good question. You know, that's an interesting question. Let's say
he testifies in the opposite direction. ושהיה איש פלוני יוצא מבית הספר
לטבול ולאכול בתרומה. V'shaya ish ploni yotzei mibeis hasefer litbol u'le'chol b'terumah.
And this kid, whether they would leave חדר cheder and this kid
would always... the father would take him and they'd go dunk in
the מקווה mikvah and then always have these תרומה terumah meals. I
don't know how you know it's תרומה. terumah. ודילמא עבד כהן הוא?
V'dilma eved kohen hu? So this is Michael's question. How do you
know that means that he was a כהן? kohen? Maybe he was
the slave of a כהן? kohen? מסייע ליה לרבי יהושע בן לוי.
Mesayei lei l'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Maybe this supports רבי יהושע בן
לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אסור לאדם
שילמד עבדו תורה. D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi asur l'adam sheyelameid avdo
Torah. A person cannot teach his slave תורה, Torah, right? We know
about the statement in the משנה, mishnah, at least one תנא, Tanna,
about not being מלמד בתו תורה. melameid bito Torah. Here it's not...
teaching your slave תורה. Torah. Okay, so therefore if he went to
the חדר, Cheder, obviously he wasn’t a slave. The גמרא Gemara says,
right, which is interesting. Presumably the reason is, I mean like we
know, you know from the South and so on, you want to
keep the slaves uneducated because education is this is tremendous you know
gives them an enormous amount of power, so keeping people uneducated keeps
them down, you know, and also presumably also doesn't confuse in this
case in terms specifically of תורה, Torah, you know that maybe what
they're like you know that they are well I guess it's the
same point, but it doesn't it doesn't blur the boundaries of whether
who's you know about whether they're slave or free.
What slave is this? What kind of עבד eved is this?
What this is an עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani, a non-Jewish slave.
So an עבד כנעני Eved Kena'ani is on the way to גיור,
giyur, don't you teach him some תורה? Torah?
He's only on the way to גיור giyur if you're going to
free him. They basically wouldn't free their עבדים כנעניים. avadim Kena'anim. It
would be a rare exception that they would free them.
They have to keep some מצוות. mitzvos.
Yeah, you teach them the הלכה, halacha, but you don't send them
to חדר Cheder and teach them school. לאו, Lo, is that really
true, you do not do that? שמע תניא, Shema tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Baraisa, לוה הימנו רבו. Laveh heimenu rabbo. So לוה
הימנו רבו, Laveh heimenu rabbo, if a master did any of the
following things we're going to say a list, it might be want
to be seen as an indicator that this person is no longer
a slave, but that's not the case. So number one, the master
borrowed money from him. You tend not to borrow money from your
slaves. But anyway as we know in the Roman Empire some slaves
were extremely wealthy, some slaves owned slaves. Anyway, so if the master
borrowed money from him, או שעשאו רבו אפוטרופוס, o she'asao rabbo apitropos,
or the master made him a an אפוטרופוס apitropos like a guardian,
right, or some type as an overseer of his estate, like יוסף.
Yosef. Okay, או שהניח תפילין בפני רבו, o she'heni'ach tefillin bifnei rabbo,
or he put on תפילין, tefillin, right? Slaves are are not obligated
in תפילין, tefillin, they're like מצוות, mitzvos, and doing it in the
presence of the master is basically a normally one would think that
that's a way of expressing the fact that I'm a free Jew.
Okay, או שקרא שלשה פסוקים בבית
הכנסת, o she'kara shelosha pesukim b'veit hakeneset, or you gave him an
עליה. aliyah. He read three פסוקים pesukim in the שול. shul. הרי
זה לא יצא לחירות. harei zeh lo yatza l'cheirus.
He does not go out to freedom. Even though all these things
might be seen as indicators that he's free, somehow we say it's
possible that slaves would do this even if he was not free.
The most interesting one is the בית הכנסת, beit hakeneset, right? Who
is the one who gave him an עליה? aliyah? All these other
things, it's a little different. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says, you see they that he can read
תורה, Torah, he knows how to read תורה, Torah, and nevertheless it's
not an indicator that he's free. So if it really is forbidden
to teach your slave תורה, Torah, why is the reading of the
תורה Torah not a proof that he's not a slave? So the
גמרא Gemara says no. התם דאקרי עבד מדעתו. Hatam d'akrei eved mida'ato.
No, there he read it on his own, meaning maybe we didn't
give him an עליה aliyah and certainly he was self-taught. Okay, to
be self-taught and to go ahead and be able to read פסוקים
pesukim doesn't prove that you're free. But כי קאמינא דקנוי ביה מנהג
בנים, ki ka'amina d'kanoi bei minhag banim, that what are we saying
about that you're not allowed to teach your slave תורה, Torah, דקנוי
ביה מנהג בנים, d'kanoi bei minhag banim,
that we're talking about like basically sending him to school. You don't
go ahead and send your slave to your you know to your
Jewish day school. Okay, so therefore the fact that the the kid
went from the בית ספר beit sefer and to be טובל ואוכל
בתרומה tovel v'ocheil b'trumah is a proof that he's a כהן Kohen
and not a slave of a כהן, Kohen, because you're not supposed
to give a formal education to a formal Jewish education you're not
supposed to give to your slave. Okay, and therefore if this guy
was getting a formal Jewish education, slaves might be a little bit
self-taught or whatever, but don't give a formal Jewish education. All right,
again it is fascinating because for how long women went without a
formal education, right, and the discussions of not teaching a woman תורה
Torah and so on. All right.
How is it that a כנעני Kena'ani slave gets an עליה? aliyah?
Yeah, that I don't understand. Maybe שלשה פסוקים shelosha pesukim did not
mean an עליה, aliyah, maybe he just סתם stam read it in
the שול. shul. Okay, although שלשה פסוקים shelosha pesukim is funny because
it sounds like that. Read it for himself. Yeah, exactly, I don't
know. All right, moving on. לטבול ולאכול בתרומה, L'tvol u'le'echol b'trumah, so
we go to the מקוה mikvah and eat תרומה. trumah. בתרומה, B'trumah,
now we get to back to the question of okay, we understand
why we're assuming he's not a slave, but why do we believe
this person, right? Normally you you require real testimony and you only
saw it as a kid. So we say בתרומה דרבנן. b'trumah d'rabbanan.
We're only going to believe he's a כהן Kohen enough to allow
him to eat תרומה דרבנן. trumah d'rabbanan. Again, we're going to believe
this person what he saw as a kid for rabbinic matters or
for matters that don't really need formal testimony. Okay, so we've got
the כתובה kesubah issue, which we generally would assume it was a
first marriage. We've got the קיום שטרות kiyom shtaros validating signatures, which
generally we assume of which is only a rabbinic requirement. And now
we've got believing somebody that somebody is a כהן, Kohen, but we
only believe him for the sake of eating תרומה. trumah. ושהיה חולק
עמנו על הגורן, V'shehayah cholek immanu al hagoren, תרומה דרבנן, trumah d'rabbanan,
I'm sorry, thank you. ושהיה חולק עמנו על הגורן, V'shehayah cholek immanu
al hagoren, and that he would come with us to the to
the threshing floor and to get a portion of the grain, again
proving he's a כהן. Kohen. So again the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא
עבד כהן הוא, v'dilma eved Kohen hu, maybe he's the slave of
a כהן. Kohen. You know, by the case of the school you
prove that a כהן Kohen wouldn't get a formal education, but here
maybe he's the slave of a כהן. Kohen. תנן כמאן דאמר אין
חולקין תרומה לעבד אלא אם כן רבו עמו. Tnan k'man d'amar: Ein
cholkin trumah l'eved ella im kein rabbo immo. So this משנה Mishnah
is like the position that says you don't give to the slave
of a כהן Kohen unless the רבו, rabbo, unless the master is
there. And therefore if this person was getting by himself, you assume
he actually was the כהן Kohen and not the slave of a
כהן. Kohen. Now why would you not give to the slave of
without the master? Exactly because these things are like very much intertwined,
because then people will infer that he's actually a כהן. Cohen. So
if you're in a type of a place that
מעלין maalin מטרומה ליוחסין, mi-terumah le-yichusin, that if somebody gets תרומה, terumah,
they will assume that therefore he is a כהן Cohen for יוחסין
yichusin purposes, then you are going to say it's going to be
אסור assur because people will make that inference or maybe that's the
law, therefore it's going to be אסור assur to give to the
כהן Cohen to give to somebody without the master being there, to
give to a slave because people are going to interpret if he's
getting it, he must be a כהן. Cohen. Once it's אסור assur
to give to somebody unless the master is there, that of course
then reinforces the idea that if anybody is getting תרומה, terumah, he
must actually be the כהן. Cohen. So obviously these two like go
hand in hand, it's a little chicken and egg. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ומשתכח דמפעי ליה תרומה? u-mishtakach de-maf'ei leh terumah?
Yeah, yeah, that's the whole point. Right. דתניא de-tanya תנו רבנן tnu
rabanan ברייתא. braisa. אין חולקין תרומה לעבד אלא אם כן רבו עמו,
ein cholkin terumah le'eved ela im ken rabo imo, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yehuda. You don't give תרומה terumah to a slave unless
the master is there. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי
יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer
יכול הוא שיאמר, yachol hu she-yomar, now, okay, this is a special
case where basically
a free woman and her slave woman both gave birth to babies
at the same time, and the babies got mixed up, and they're
two boys. So one of these boys is the master and the
other is the slave of one another, you just don't know who's
who. So the question is how do they collect תרומה? terumah? Okay,
really what it says is that they're supposed to free one another
and then whatever, but fine. Until that point, how do they collect
תרומה? terumah? So one opinion is that have them go together, okay,
and therefore they'll both say one of us is the master, one
is the slave, give us one portion of תרומה. terumah. אין חולקין
תרומה לעבד אלא אם כן רבו עמו, ein cholkin terumah le'eved ela
im ken rabo imo, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yose omer יכול
הוא שיאמר, yachol hu she-yomar, no,
one guy can go by himself and say the following: אם כהן
אני תנו לי בשביל עצמי. im kohen ani tnu li bishvil atzmi.
If I'm a כהן, Cohen, then I'm entitled for myself. ואם עבד
כהן אני ve-im eved kohen ani and if I'm the עבד eved
of this guy, then תנו לי בשביל רבי, tnu li bishvil rabi,
give me for my רבי. Rebbe. So basically it means okay, but
basically according to that opinion, you see that you can give to
the slave of a כהן Cohen without his master being there. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, במקום שרבי יהודה היה מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין,
bimkom she-Rabbi Yehuda haya maalin mi-terumah le-yichusin, in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
place they would go from somebody getting תרומה terumah to assume that
he was מיוחס meyuchas for all other aspects of כהונה. kehuna. And
therefore, if that's true, you don't give to somebody... you don't give
to a slave without the master being there. במקום שרבי יוסי לא
היה מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין, bimkom she-Rabbi Yose lo haya maalin mi-terumah le-yichusin,
in רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose place they would not assume that just
because you got תרומה terumah you were therefore a כהן, Cohen, maybe
you were the slave of a כהן. Cohen. And therefore you could
give to the slave without the master. These go hand in hand.
That's a proclamation!
What? That's a proclamation, it fits perfectly.
Right. דתניא de-tanya תנו רבנן tnu rabanan ברייתא, braisa, אמר רבי אלעזר
בר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose, מימי לא העדתי,
mi-yamai lo he'edati, in my life I was very scrupulous not to
give testimony, I didn't want חס ושלום chas veshalom God forbid want
to make a mistake or want my testimony to lead to somebody
else, you know, something wrong happening. Of course the problem is, you
know, not making a decision is also a decision, if you don't
give testimony it also could affect somebody's... you know, somebody needed your
testimony. But anyway, he says I never gave testimony, and here's basically
the lesson I learned. פעם אחת העדתי, paam achas he'edati, the one
time I decided to give testimony, העלו עבד לכהונה על פי, he'alu
eved le-kehuna al pi, and it wound up that it was misunderstood
or whatever or they drew the wrong inference and I misunderstood it,
anyway it wound up that an עבד eved was treated as a
כהן. Cohen. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says: העלו סלקא דעתך? he'alu
salka daatach? Do we really think that
happened, that they treated this עבד eved as
a כהן? Cohen? והשתא מה בהמתן של צדיקים אין הקדוש ברוך הוא
מביא תקלה על ידם, ve-hashta ma-behemtan shel tzadikim ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu
mevi takala al yadam,
if God doesn't cause even the animals of the righteous to sin,
meaning the story about the donkey of פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas ben
Yair that would not accidentally eat things that were not... that were
טבל tevel or something. So if that's true, צדיקים עצמן לא כל
שכן? tzadikim atzman lo kol sheken? How much more so would God
not let the righteous people themselves sin? So it can't really be
that this happened. אלא בקשו להעלות עבד לכהונה על פי. ela bikshu
le-haalos eved le-kehuna al pi. They wanted to, they were about to,
and somehow at the last minute they realized the mistake. Now what
happened? חזייא באתרא דרבי יוסי, chazya b'asra de-Rabbi Yose, he saw in
the place of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose somebody getting תרומה, terumah, okay,
and in the place of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose an עבד eved
could get תרומה terumah by himself. So he saw somebody getting תרומה
terumah by himself in the place of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. ואזל
ואסהיד באתרא דרבי יהודה. ve-azal ve-saheid b'asra de-Rabbi Yehuda. And he gave
testimony in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda place. I saw this guy get
תרומה terumah by himself in this rest influence... and רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda place says oh it must be that he's a כהן Cohen
because here we don't give anybody by themselves unless they're a כהן.
Cohen. Problem was, was that the event had happened in רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yose place where you do get תרומה terumah if you're not
a כהן. Cohen. I mean, if you're the slave of a כהן
Cohen even if your master is not there. So that's how the
testimony of one place became misunderstood in the other place and they
made this mistake. By the way, this idea that אין הקדוש ברוך
הוא מביא תקלה, ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mevi takala, you know, תוספות
Tosfos in a number of places says there's all these examples about
righteous people inadvertently sinning and there's a... right,
well besides that but in the גמרא, Gemara, the אמוראים, Amoraim, there's
one case talking about like דין, din, who was it about this
person who killed these 80 witches or something?
שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben
Shetach, and the whole case about the עדים זוממים. eidim zomemim. So
תוספות Tosfos says this is specifically a around eating food you're not
supposed to be eating. Like, you know, the whole story about this
donkey of פנחס בן יאיר. Pinchas ben Yair. Fascinating the type of
special taboo that's seen about sort of introducing טריף traife food into
your body. So therefore it says that if they didn't do this
with what do you call it, you know, so, so presumably the
relationship here is, it's not exactly him eating טריף, traife, but if
they're gonna let this עבד eved be treated as a כהן, kohen,
although it's funny because what are they gonna do? He's already eating
תרומה. terumah. Yeah, I don't know. This doesn't exactly work into that
structure. Anyway, fine. But that's what we see, that the question about
you believe the guy number one because you're not afraid that he's
an עבד eved because he's being getting a formal education. And you're
not afraid he's an עבד eved if he goes to the granary
because it's a place where they make sure that only the masters
go, or only the slaves go with their masters, but not no
slaves go. And therefore you can believe the person what he saw
in his youth because you're believing him only for the purposes of
תרומה דרבנן. terumah d'rabbanan. So Tommy, Michael, we have six minutes to
get to the end of the דף. daf. Okay. ומקום הזה בית
הפרס. V'shemakom hazeh beis hapras. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason?
So, בית הפרס דרבנן, beis hapras d'rabbanan, cause the whole problem of
going in a בית הפרס, beis hapras, which is a field in
which a grave has been plowed over, is rabbinic. And therefore, again,
we're going to believe you for rabbinic matter. דאמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל: D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: מנפח אדם בית הפרס והולך. Menape'ach
adam beis hapras v'holeich. You can blow the area in front of
you to check for little chips of bone and walk through בית
הפרס, beis hapras, which we wouldn't let you do obviously if there
was a biblical concern. ורב יהודה בר אמי משמיה דרב יהודה אמר:
V'Rav Yehuda bar Ami mishmei d'Rav Yehuda amar: בית הפרס שנידוש טהור.
beis hapras shenidash tahor. If the בית הפרס beis hapras has been
sort of trampled through, then it's okay. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's
the reason? אי אפשר לעצם כשעורה שלא נידוש ברגל. Iy efshar l'etzem
k'se'orah shelo nidash b'regel. That even if you have a tiny chip
of bone, if people have really made a very well-trodden path through
it, then even those chips will be so small that they will
no longer be big enough—they'll be smaller than a barley bean. Pretty
amazing that you could think that that's how small everything is going
to get. Anyway, and therefore it will not make somebody טמא. tamei.
Okay, anyway, all that proves that these are rabbinic concerns and therefore
we will believe somebody what they saw as a minor. עד כאן
היינו באים בשבת. Ad kan hayinu ba'im b'shabbos. We would only go
up to this place on שבת, Shabbos, or up to—we'd go as
far as this place, so maybe you'll believe him to be מקל.
meikal. So the גמרא Gemara says: קסבר תחומים דרבנן. Kasavar techumin d'rabbanan.
We're assuming that the idea of תחומים techumin is rabbinic. ואין נאמן
לומר דרך היה לפלוני במקום הזה מעמד ומיספד היה לפלוני במקום הזה.
V'ein ne'eman lomar derech hayah l'ploni b'makom hazeh, ma'amad u'misped hayah l'ploni
b'makom hazeh. But you're not believed to say that this person, I
saw that he would always have the right to go through this
field, you know, to cut through it, or he has the right
to have his funeral processions here, which would give somebody actual property
rights, which is a straight case of דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos, which
you need formal testimony, and you need somebody to have seen even
as an adult. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אפוקי ממונא
לא מפקינן. Afukei mamona lo mafkinan. We are not going to take
money away from somebody, right, without there being actual formal testimony. תנו
רבנן: Tano rabbonan: נאמן תינוק לומר—an Ne'eman tinok lomar infant is believed
to say—כך אמר לי אבא, kach amar li abba, this is what
my father said, משפחה זו טהורה משפחה זו טמאה. mishpachah zu tehorah,
mishpachah zu tmeiah. This family is טהורה tehorah or טמאה. tmeiah. So
the גמרא Gemara says: טהורה וטמאה סלקא דעתך? Tehorah u'tmeiah salka da'atach?
How could you have families that are טהורה tehorah or טמאה? tmeiah?
אלא—so Ela it was a euphemism, well, not a euphemism—משפחה זו כשירה
משפחה זו פסולה. mishpachah zu ksheirah, mishpachah zu psulah. This family is
כשירה, ksheirah, this is פסולה, psulah, maybe in terms of the question
of like whether there's a problem of them being כהנים kohanim and
so on, you know, being חללים challalim amongst them or ממזרים mamzerim
amongst them. Now, that's pretty dangerous now, because now we're believing him
even for, you know, for personal status issues and not just for
תרומה דרבנן, terumah d'rabbanan, but for more radical things.
ושכננו בקצצה שבת פלוני לפלוני. V'shachannu b'ktzatza shebas ploni l'ploni. And we
ate at the קצצה ktzatza of when this person's daughter was married
to this other guy. Now, what does that mean? We'll see in
the גמרא. Gemara. ושהיינו מוליכין חלה ומתנות לפלוני כהן על ידי עצמו.
V'shehayinu molichin challah u'matanos l'ploni kohen al yedei atzmo. And I—we would
bring, you know, חלה, challah, and—which, you know, the separation of חלה
challah from the dough—and the מתנות, matanos, which would be the portions
of the animal that you would give to the כהן, kohen, to
this person as a כהן, kohen, if he himself went to deliver
them. אבל לא על ידי אחר. Aval lo al yedei achair. But
he's not believed to say that we sent somebody else to deliver
them, because who knows where in the end that person went. So
again, the issue about that we would—I would deliver חלה challah and
these sections of the animal to this guy shows that we can
have evidence that the guy is a כהן. kohen.
Okay, but the first thing...
he can't eat that? Well, never could eat that. But again, maybe
that's not the type of thing you would give to an עבד.
eved. I don't know, it's a good question.
Okay. וכולן—and V'chulan all these cases... Okay, but we don't know what
the קצצה ktzatza case is and we don't know what this כשירה
ופסולה ksheira u'psula case is, or we do know what the כשירה
ופסולה ksheira u'psula case is, but that's much more graphic than everything
we've been saying.
וכולן—all V'chulan these cases that we said that you believe somebody what
they saw as a
minor—אם היה עובד כוכבים ונתגייר. im hayah akum v'nisgayer. If they were
a non-Jew and then they converted. Okay, another case of not seeing
it as a kosher עד eid and now being kosher. He was
a non-Jew and he witnessed these things, and now he's converted. עבד
ונשתחרר—or Eved v'nishtachrer a slave who witnessed them and now he's freed.
So, similar to having been a minor when you saw them, you
were a slave or a non-Jew when you saw them, and now
you're freed, and now you're Jewish, can you testify what you saw
in that prior state? אין נאמנין. Ein ne'emanin. They're not believed. ואין
נאמן לומר דרך היה לפלוני במקום הזה מעמד ומיספד היה לפלוני במקום
הזה. V'ein ne'eman lomar derech hayah l'ploni b'makom hazeh, ma'amad u'misped hayah
l'ploni b'makom hazeh. And you're not believed to say that this person
had, you know, this right of way through this other guy's field.
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר נאמנין. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka omer ne'emanin.
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says they are believed.
This statement "they are believed" goes back to having been a non-Jew
or slave. So this is basically the structure of our משנה, mishnah,
but it's introduced a few new things. about what happens if somebody
had been a slave or non-Jew and now is freed; are they
believed what they saw at that stage? And these other two cases
about this קצצה Ketzatzah and this משפחה כשירה משפחה פסולה. mishpacha k'sheira
mishpacha psula. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Why is מעמד ומושב ma'amad u'moshav an issue of money?
Because if you have the right to use the field for that
purpose. It's שמעון's Shimon's field, but when ראובן Reuven would go to
the
cemetery outside of the city, he would have a right to stop
his procession and to have all these whole types of events. You
walk through and also right and also have these whole events take
place there, etc. So now the גמרא Gemara says האי, hai, which
one is רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka going on?
When he says he would believe them. אילימא סיפא, Ilema seifa, if
it's for the issue about like the right of way through somebody's
field, אפוקי ממונא הוא, afukei mamona hu, you know how can he
believe anybody? That's real דיני ממונות. dinei mamonus. אלא ארישא, Ela areisha,
it must be the case right before that. וכולן אם היה עובד
כוכבים ונתגייר עבד ונשתחרר אין נאמנים, V'kullan im haya akum v'nisgayer eved
v'nishtachrer ein ne'emanim,
that if somebody was a non-Jew or slave when they saw something
and now they're free, they are not believed. It's not like being
a minor. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר נאמנים, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
omer ne'emanim, they are believed. So במאי קמיפלגי, b'mai kamiflei, what's the
debate? Now you might I might have thought the debate was a
more formalistic one. It's one thing to have been young and Jewish
as opposed to being completely out of the category, like a slave
or non-Jew, right? Then you're not like you're not even like a
not yet kosher witness, you're like not even in the same conversation.
But the גמרא Gemara makes it more of a question about how
much we can say you really paid attention to what you saw.
תנא קמא סבר כיון דעובד כוכבים הוא לא הוה דייק, Tanna Kama
savar kivan d'akum hu lo hadei dayik,
since he was a non-Jew or slave, you like it wasn't maybe
this is also the issue of relevance, but not from a formal
sense, but from a psychological sense. What things that were happening in
the Jewish world, what did he understand of them? He wasn't going
to pay attention or he doesn't going to really understand what it
all meant. And therefore well that's what רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה סבר
כיון דדעתיה לאיגיורי מהוה דייק שפיר, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka savar kivan
d'daiteih l'igiyurei mah daik yifei, since he's planning on converting, he's paying
attention. Of course, what happens if he saw it before he was
in the process of converting? What happens if a slave saw it?
A slave isn't in the process of becoming free. How do we
know? But of course you know that he's going to be free.
It could have been a מסיח לפי תומו. masiach l'fi tumo. It's
like a perfect מסיח לפי
תומו.
masiach
l'fi tumo.
Well, that's also true, we've had that's a good point too, we
have had מסיח לפי תומו, masiach l'fi tumo, and if part of
the problem is that you don't like so anyway, so that's interesting
about that debate. Now, מאי קצצה, mai ketzatzah, again the גמרא Gemara
does not discuss this issue about this family is כשרה k'sheira this
is פסולה psula which sounds like we really believe him to פסול
posul a whole a whole family, you know, that sounds pretty radical.
The גמרא Gemara just skips over that. And now we're getting to
this קצצה ketzatzah case. Okay. So מאי קצצה, mai ketzatzah, what is
this קצצה ketzatzah thing? תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, rabbis taught. כיצד קצצה
אחד מן האחים שנשא אשה שאינה הגונה לו,
Keitzad ketzatzah echad min
ha'achim shenasa isha she'eina hogenes lo, if one of the brothers married
a woman beneath his status, באין בני משפחה ומביאין חבית מלאה פירות,
ba'in bnei mishpacha u'mevi'in chavit m'leia peiros,
so the family comes and they make a public shaming of him
apparently, they bring a barrel filled with fruit, okay, ושוברין אותה באמצע,
v'shovrin osa b'emtza, and
they break it in half, באמצע רחובה, b'emtza rechova, in half of
its width, and presumably then the fruit all spills out.
ואומרים באמצע רחובה משום
V'omerim b'emtza
rechova m'shum
oh you're right, I'm sorry, you're totally right, I misread that. In
the middle of the street, thank you, באמצע רחובה b'emtza rechova they
break it in the middle of the street, they make a public
spectacle out of it. ואומרים V'omerim and they say, אחינו בית ישראל,
acheinu beis Yisrael, our brother the Jewish people brethren the Jewish people,
שמעו shimu listen, אחינו acheinu please listen our brethren, פלוני נשא אשה
שאינה הגונה לו, ploni nasa isha she'eina hogenes lo, this guy married
a woman unbefitting to him, ומתיראים אנו שמא יתערב זרעו בזרענו, u'misyar'im
anu shema yisarev zaro b'zareinu, and we don't want his kids to
intermarry in our kids because they're all going to be of a
lowly status cause this woman is from a lowly status. Don't think
just cause he comes from our family that his kids have that
same level of ייחוס. yichus. They are no longer have that ייחוס.
yichus. You see how weighty these ייחוס yichus issues are. I mean,
so much of this פרק perek was about יוחסין יוחסין yuchsin yuchsin
and we didn't even understand what's the halakhic aspect of יוחסין yuchsin
wasn't always clear but you see how weighty it was. So this
they'll even do to their own family member to say like as
a way of like don't let and in a way also what
this is doing is it's protecting them. Don't let this bring down
our family and the status of our family. We are pushing this
guy out, we don't want, you know, you shouldn't marry into him,
we don't want to marry into him, don't make don't have that
reflect badly on us. Okay. וקחו לכם דוגמא לדורות שלא יתערב זרעו
בזרענו, V'kachu lachem dugma l'doros shelo yisarev zaro b'zareinu, take from this
an example for generations shelo yisarev zaro b'zareinu, his seed shouldn't intermarry
our seed, he's no longer part of our family. וזו היא קצצה
שהתינוק נאמן להעיד עליה, V'zu hi ketzatzah shehatinok ne'eman l'ha'id aleha, so
this is the קצצה ketzatzah
that a kid could go ahead and testify on. I'm not exactly
sure what it's saying so what do we learn from it? We
learn that that he married a woman beneath his status, we learn
from it ייחוס yichus information, presumably we learn from it ייחוס yichus
information which again raises the question of how halakhic is ייחוס yichus
information. I should say while we end this פרק perek that let's
also remember talking about the first weddings that they would go ahead
and take the barrel of wine and the whole barrel of wine
would be the symbolism, you know, that they would use in terms
of a woman and a virgin and so on. So of course
what happens in that barrel if you have kids they become fruit,
right? So the barrel of wine where the wine is the you
know hymenal blood and so on, etc., in this metaphor, it's a
barrel filled with fruit because it's the fruit that The Pampas region
in Argentina is an extensive agricultural plain, known worldwide for its productivity
and quality in grain and meat production.
In recent decades, this region has undergone significant changes in its landscapes
and production systems, with
direct consequences for the environment and the services it provides.
In this context, INTA and FAUBA researchers carried out a
collaborative study to
evaluate how agriculture, especially The substitution of perennial pastures with annual crops
has affected the
storage and capture
of organic carbon in the soil. The research, led by specialists such
as Gervasio Piñeiro and José Volanteunderlined the central role of
the soil as a carbon sink, which is essential to reduce the
levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere and face climate change. However,
land use change in the Pampean region has altered this function. Through
a massive analysis of data provided by producers, which include more than
30,000 data from the last 20 yearsthe researchers found that the soils
of the Pampean region have lost a significant amount of organic carbon.
This phenomenon is mainly due to the decrease in the surface area
destined to perennial pastures (such as alfalfa) and the expansion of the
monoculture of annual crops, such as soybeans and corn. According to José
Volantegeneral coordinator of the project Foresight INTA, “This research addresses the challenges
of agriculture in the Pampean region in a context of global changes.
We focus specifically on soil organic carbon, a critical component not only
for agricultural productivity, but also for the environmental health of the planet.
The study is unique because it uses real data from producerswhich gives
it great relevance and precision.” The results indicated that the transition from
mixed systems (livestock-agriculture) towards purely agricultural systems has led to a lower
input of carbon to the soil. Perennial pasturesare capable of capturing and
storing carbon in a more effective and stable way than annual crops,
which remain in the soil for a shorter time and provide less
organic matter. Furthermore, the study indicates that soil organic carbon storage varies
significantly by subregion. For example, the Southern Pampa has shown a greater
loss of carbon in comparison with other areas, which suggests the need
to implement specific management practices for each zone. To reverse this trend,
researchers suggest the adoption of best management practices (BPA), such as No-till,
cover crops and the reincorporation of perennial pastures into rotating systems. These
practices not only help to recover and store more carbon in the
soil, but also improve its structure, fertility and water retention capacity. As
stated by the researchers, “the key is to find a balance between
agricultural productivity and environmental sustainability. The results of this study provide a
fundamental scientific basis for the design of policies and strategies that promote
more sustainable management of the Pampean territory, ensuring its long-term health.” The
project, which included the participation of several INTA experimental stations and FAUBA,
highlights the importance of collaborative work and the use of big data
in agricultural research. The study not only warns about current losses, but
also offers a path towards the climate change mitigation through more sustainable
agriculture.